Finding Aid for the RecorDIM Project Records of the Getty Conservation Institute Field Projects Division, 1994-2009, undated IA10016
Institutional Records and Archives
RecorDIM project records
1994-2009,
undated
Institutional Records and Archives
Getty Conservation Institute. Field Projects Division
J. Paul Getty Trust
LeBlanc, François, 1946-
Gray, Christopher
Letellier, Robin
Eppich, Rand
IA10016
5.58 Linear Feet (10 boxes, including 7 audiocassettes)
18.91 GB (21,558 files)
Records comprise reports, meeting materials and handouts, correspondence and memoranda, budgets, contracts, publication development and design material, images, audiocassettes, and ARIS workshop materials, dating 1994-2009 and undated, created and maintained by the Field Projects Division of the Getty Conservation Institute. The materials concern the development, operation, and results of Field Projects' Recording, Documentation, and Information Management (RecorDIM) Initiative. Some of the planning, publication, and ARIS workshop materials are in digital form, consisting of text, database, PowerPoint, image, website, and CAD files. The majority of the records were authored by project director and Field Projects Head, François LeBlanc, and by consultant Robin Letellier. Some of the files were also maintained by Christopher Gray, a senior project specialist in Field Projects, and Rand Eppich, project specialist and manager of the Institute's Digital Lab.
Related Materials Note
The following materials are offered as possible sources of further information on the people, programs, and subjects covered by the records. The listing is not exhaustive.
Publications
Eppich, Rand, and Amel Chabbi, eds. 2007. Recording, Documentation and Information Management for the Conservation of Heritage Places: Illustrated Examples. Los Angeles, CA: Getty Conservation Institute. http://hdl.handle.net/10020/gci_pubs/recordim_vol2
Letellier, Robin, Werner Schmid, and François LeBlanc. 2007. > Recording, Documentation, and Information Management for the Conservation of Heritage Places: Guiding Principles. Los Angeles, CA: Getty Conservation Institute. http://hdl.handle.net/10020/gci_pubs/recordim
Letellier, Robin and Christopher Gray. 2002. Bridging the gap between information users and information providers [electronic resource]: Recording, Documentation and Information Management (RecorDIM) Initiative: report of Roundtable 1, Los Angeles, California, March 4-5, 2002. Los Angeles, CA: Getty Conservation Institute. [Getty Internet Access, NA2728 .B75]
Additional RecorDIM project publications can be accessed at http://www.getty.edu/conservation/our_projects/field_projects/recordim/recordim_publications.html.
Appraisal
Projects of the Conservation Institute's Field Projects Division are considered archival, documenting work and research done on international cultural heritage sites and issues. In accordance with internal Field Projects procedures, the project manager of each field project will select and prepare for transfer to the Institutional Archives the project documentation required to ensure that future researchers and conservators will understand past work done on each site and to provide a foundation for future work.
Alternate Form Available
Electronic versions of some of these documents may still be stored in the originating department.
Acquisition Information
Accessions 2007.IA.38, 2018.IA.27, and 2019.IA.20 were transferred by Field Projects, Getty Conservation Institute.
Technical Requirements
Access to digital content in 2007.IA.38, 2018.IA.27, and 2019.IA.20 is only available on-site.
Please note that we may not be able to provide access to all file formats due to lack of required software and/or system specifications. For more information, contact Library Reference at the Getty Research Institute.
Access Restrictions
With the exception of materials that have been marked restricted or confidential, the records described in accession 2007.IA.38, 2018.IA.27, and 2019.IA.20 are available for use by qualified researchers. Please note: selected restricted materials must be removed from boxes prior to access by researchers.
The following records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Access to digital content in the collection is only available on Getty networked computers and in the Special Collections Reading Room.
Scope and Content of Collection
Records comprise reports, meeting materials and handouts, correspondence and memoranda, budgets, contracts, publication development and design material, images, audiocassettes, and ARIS workshop materials, dating 1994-2009 and undated, created and maintained by the Field Projects Division of the Getty Conservation Institute. The materials concern the development, operation, and results of Field Projects' Recording, Documentation, and Information Management (RecorDIM) Initiative. Some of the planning, publication, and ARIS workshop materials are in digital form, consisting of text, database, PowerPoint, image, website, and CAD files. The majority of the records were authored by project director and Field Projects Head, François LeBlanc, and by consultant Robin Letellier. Some of the files were also maintained by Christopher Gray, a senior project specialist in Field Projects, and Rand Eppich, project specialist and manager of the Institute's Digital Lab.
Arrangement
These records are arranged into components in accordance with the GCI Field Projects project management system. Records are arranged in the following categories: Administration, Bibliographies, Component 1 - International Coordination, Component 2 - Publication - Guiding Principles, Component 3 - Publication - Illustrated Examples, Component 4 - Website, Component 5 - Training, Component 6 - Publication - Metric Survey, Component 7 - Monitoring and Evaluation, Manuals and Standards, Reports, and Visuals.
Administrative History
The Getty Conservation Institute (GCI), a part of the J. Paul Getty Trust, was initially planned in 1982 and began full operation in 1985. Since its inception, the GCI has engaged in a program of scientific research, educational activities, documentation, and the dissemination of information through publications, conferences, workshops, and public programs that include research opportunities for professionals and public lectures. In addition, the Institute has conducted international field projects in Asia, Africa, North and South America, and Europe. The GCI's endeavors are designed to serve the needs of the conservation profession by undertaking work that tackles broad practical or theoretical questions of significance to the conservation field. The Institute develops and refines tools for conservation and shares its expertise with institutions and organizations worldwide so that its efforts have the greatest possible benefit to the practice of conservation.
As a part of its mission, the GCI undertakes conservation projects in partnership in various parts of the world. For the purpose of bringing together information users and providers in the field of heritage conservation, one of these projects was with the International Center for the Study of the Preservation and the Restoration of Cultural Property (ICCROM) and the International Scientific Committee for Documentation of Cultural Heritage (CIPA), a committee of the International Council of Monuments and Sites (ICOMOS) and the International Society for Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing (ISPRS). The project, known as the Recording, Documentation and Information Management (RecorDIM) Initiative, was intended to explore ways for the GCI to contribute in partnership to raise the level of conservation practice through more effective and improved use of recording, documentation, and information management as a strategic component for the conservation of monuments and sites. The Initiative had its genesis in 1995 when, under the guidance of Robin Letellier, CIPA assembled outreach workshops after its general meetings. The workshop groups found that gaps existed between the users and providers of information for built cultural heritage projects. To identify the gaps and to find strategic ways to fill them, the concept of "Bridging the Gap" was introduced by the GCI in 2000. By 2002 this had become the RecorDIM Initiative, which started with a roundtable held at the Getty Center identifying twenty-five gaps between the information users and providers.
The GCI intended, with the help of partners, to focus on the following: the publication of a manual on Principles and Guidelines for the recording, documentation, and information management of built cultural heritage; the publication of a handbook on the same subject; and the creation and support of a web presence. The program was later expanded to include training initiatives, which were carried out through Architectural Records, Inventories, and Information Systems for Conservation (ARIS) courses, initially organized by ICCROM and later co-sponsored by the GCI.
The group of core collaborators included CIPA, English Heritage, Public Works and Government Services Canada, World Monument Fund, ICOMOS, and the GCI. To accomplish the work 20 international task groups were formed to focus on specific needs and five roundtable meetings were held at various international venues. As part of the training component, four ARIS courses were held in Rome from 2005 to 2009 on documentation methodologies and tools, providing training to 59 mid-career professionals from over 46 countries.
The Initiative lasted from 2002 through 2007 and the project was managed by, first, Field Project staff member Christopher Gray and then by department head François LeBlanc. Robin Letellier was hired as a consultant to coordinate the Initiative at the international level. Rand Eppich, project specialist and manager of the GCI's Digital Lab, was also a member of the project team and led the ARIS courses.
Historic sites -- Conservation and restoration -- Data processing; Information technology -- Management; Drafts (documents); Information storage and retrieval systems -- Architecture; Photogrammetry in architecture; Correspondence; Reports; Knowledge management; Digital images; Budgets; Monuments -- Recording; Electronic documents; International Committee of Architectural Photogrammetry; International Council of Monuments and Sites
- Administration
  - Agreements (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    Access Restrictions
    Access to agreements is limited to GCI and Trust Administration staff.
    - FY 2002 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    - FY 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    - FY 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    - FY 2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    - FY 2006-FY 2007 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
  - Budgets (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    Access to budgets is limited to GCI and Trust Administration staff.
    - FY 2002 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    - FY 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    - FY 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    - FY 2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    - FY 2006 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    - FY 2007 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
    - FY 2008 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 6)
  - Contacts, 2006 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
  - Correspondence, 1997-1998; 2002-2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
  - Getty Conservation Institute filing procedures, 2001-2002 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Drafts and notes for Christopher Gray's documentation protocol document.
    Access to digital files in 2007.IA.38 is available to on-site researchers and Getty staff. Contact Library Reference at the Getty Research Institute for information about these files or to request access.
  - Permissions [includes copyright permissions for the Guiding Principles publication], 2006-2007 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
  - Planning documents, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
- Bibliographies
  - Bibliographies [includes remote monitoring of World Heritage Sites bibliography and Guiding Principles publication bibliography], 1994; undated (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
- Component 1 – International Coordination
  - Partners meeting, Ottawa, Canada, June 11-13, 2007; [2 folders] (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
  - Partners meeting, Rome, Italy, May 14-16, 2006 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
  - Partners meeting, Xi'an, China, 2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
  - Partners meeting, Paris, France, May 8-10, 2005; [3 folders] (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
  - Roundtable meeting, Torino, Italy, September 27-October 1, 2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
  - Meeting with Werner Schmid, Los Angeles, California, April 2-8, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
  - Partners meeting, Leuven, Belgium, April 23-25, 2004; [5 folders] (Box 2007.IA.38 - 1)
  - Roundtable meeting, Istanbul, Turkey, July 18, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Roundtable meeting, Antalya, Turkey, 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Partners meeting, Vienna, Austria, March 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Roundtable meeting, Sevilla, Spain, November 2002 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Partners meeting, London, England, 2002 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Roundtable meeting, Madrid, Spain, 2002 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Roundtable meeting, Los Angeles, California, March 2002 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Documentation strategy development documents, 2001 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Documentation strategy correspondence, 1997-1999 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Task Groups (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Decision making tool, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Getty Conservation Institute, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - General, 2002-2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Glossary of submerged heritage, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - International Committee on the Underwater Cultural Heritage, 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Information warehouse, 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Integrating heritage recording into property management, 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Low cost digital recording, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Metric survey skills, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Monitoring world heritage, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Persian Heritage Archives, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Rock art science, 2007; undated (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Stereo views, 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - Tabulation of technologies, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
    - [Task groups mid-term status summaries for Torino and Xi'an], 2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-01)
  - [Christopher Gray's electronic documentation strategy files], 1997-2002
    Access to digital files in 2019.IA.20 is available to on-site researchers and Getty staff. Contact Library Reference at the Getty Research Institute for information about these files or to request access.
    Access to letters of agreement in the set of files is limited to GCI and Trust Administration staff.
- Component 2 – Publication – Guiding Principles
  - Letellier manuscript for ICCROM [International Center for the Study of the Preservation and the Restoration of Cultural Property] – "Recording, Documentation, and Information Management for World Cultural Heritage Sites,", 1994 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Letellier manuscript for ICCROM – first revision, 1996 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Principles and Guidelines workshop, Los Angeles, California, 1996 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Publication proposal, 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Principles and Guidelines, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Guiding Principles first draft design, 2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 2)
  - Comments on draft, 2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 3)
  - Principles and Guidelines, editorial review board notes, 2005-2006 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 3)
  - Guiding Principles Final Design by Joe Molloy, 2007 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 3)
    PDF on CD of publication (not final version).
  - Printing, 2005; 2007 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 3)
  - Guiding Principles publication comments, 2004-2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 3)
  - Guiding Principles publication, draft feedback, 2007 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 3)
  - Abstracts by François LeBlanc, undated (Box 2007.IA.38 - 3)
  - Guidelines and Handbook workshop, Los Angeles, 2003; (2 folders) (Box 2018.IA.27-02)
  - Recording, Documentation, and Information Management for the Conservation of Heritage Places: Guiding Principles, 2007; (2 copies) (Box 2018.IA.27-02)
- Component 3 – Publication – Illustrated Examples
  - Contributors:
    Files contain copies of agreements, some of which are signed; correspondence; cassette recordings of phone interviews with contributors regarding their documentation process; and notes on the interviews.
    - Addison, Alonzo, 2006-2007 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Arun, Gorun, 2005-2006 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Borelli, Caterina, 2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Chabbi, Amel, 2005-2006 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Chikwanda, Geofree, 2006-2007 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Clark, Kate, 2006 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Croci, Giorgio, 2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Crosby, Tony (handbook only), 2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Dallas, Rose, 2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Elwazani, Salim, 2006 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
      Includes a cassette tape of phone interview with Salim Elwazani.
    - Jones, Kevin L., 2006-2007 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
      Includes a cassette tape of phone interview with Kevin L. Jones.
    - Kim, Soon-Kwan, 2006-2007 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Lerma Garcia, Jose Luis, 2005-2006 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
      Includes a cassette tape of phone interview with Lerma Garcia.
    - Lunnon, Sarah, 2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Matero, Frank (handbook only), 2005-2006 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
      Includes a cassette tape of phone interview with Judy Peters.
    - Ogleby, Cliff, 2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
      Includes a cassette tape of phone interview with Ogleby.
    - Oshima, Yumi ("Cow in the Sky") [design work], 2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
      Includes two CDs containing images (not all used in publication) and mockups (not final) for Planning Interventions chapter.
    - Ouimet, Christian, 2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
      Includes a cassette tape of phone interview with Ouimet.
    - Sikka, Sandeep, 2005-2006 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Siravo, Francesco, 2006 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
      Includes a cassette tape of phone interview with Siravo.
    - Tallini, Marco, 2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
    - Van Tilburg, Jo Anne, 2005-2006 (Box 2018.IA.27-03)
  - Handbook background material, circa 2006; [4 folders] (Box 2007.IA.38 - 3)
  - Meeting with John Burns, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 3)
  - Handbook mock-up, 2006 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 3)
  - Recording, Documentation, and Information Management for the Conservation of Heritage Places: Illustrated Examples, 2007; (2 copies) (Box 2018.IA.27-02)
- Component 4 – Web Site
  Related Materials
  As of April 2019, the RecorDIM website is accessible at http://extranet.getty.edu/gci/recordim/index.html.
  The website is also available through the Internet Archive's Wayback Machine: https://web.archive.org/web/20130717002141/http://extranet.getty.edu/gci/recordim/index.html.
  - Web site pages, 2004-2007 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
    Printouts of website.
- Component 5 – Training
  - ARIS03:
    - ARIS03 [course binder], 2003 (Box 2018.IA.27-01)
    - Participants Presentations, 2001-2003 (Box 2018.IA.27-02)
      Access to digital files in 2018.IA.27 is available to on-site researchers and Getty staff. Contact Library Reference at the Getty Research Institute for information about these files or to request access.
  - ARIS05:
    - ARIS05 course materials, 2005; [3 folders] (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
    - ARIS05 [course binder], 2005; (2 folders) (Box 2018.IA.27-01)
    - [ARIS05 planning], 2003-2004 (Box 2018.IA.27-02)
    - ARIS05, 2004 (Box 2018.IA.27-02)
    - ARIS05, 2003-2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-02)
    - Case Study: The surroundings of Santa Cecilia in Trastevere (Rome), 2002-2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-02)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Because the original CD contained an interactive program, 2018ia27_i02 is available as an ISO (for accessing the interactive features) and as individual files.
    - Participants contribution, 2000-2005 (Box 2018.IA.27-02)
    - Archive 1, 1999-2005
      Restricted Access
    - Archive 2, 1998-2005
    - Additional, 2005
  - ARIS07:
    - ARIS07 course preparation material, 2007 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
    - ARIS07 [course binder], 2007; (2 folders) (Box 2018.IA.27-01)
    - Multimedia, 2001-2007 (Box 2018.IA.27-02)
      Because the original CD contained an interactive program, 2018ia27_i07 is available as an ISO (for accessing the interactive features) and as individual files.
    - ARIS '07, 2001-2007
    - ARIS '07, 1992-2007
  - ARIS09:
    - ARIS09 [course binder], 2009 (Box 2018.IA.27-01)
    - ARIS09 Documentation of the frescos in the right aisle and Ponziani Chapel of Santa Cecilia, 2009 (Box 2018.IA.27-04)
  - Glossaries, 2006 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
  - Glossary, key definitions, undated (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
- Component 6 – Publication – Metric Survey
  - Metric survey, proposal for publication from English Heritage, 2007 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
- Component 7 – Monitoring and Evaluation
  - Monitoring and evaluation of RecorDIM Initiative, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
- Manuals and Standards
  - Manuals and standards for art submissions to Getty Publications, 2004; undated (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
- Reports
  - RecorDIM - Article by François LeBlanc and Christopher Gray, 2001 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
  - RecorDIM - Article by Robin Letellier, 2001 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
  - RecorDIM – Potsdam, Germany; field trip report by François LeBlanc, 2001 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
  - RecorDIM - Article by Peter Waldhaeusl, 2002 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
  - RecorDIM - Madrid, Spain; field trip report by François LeBlanc, November-December 2002 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
  - RecorDIM activities report by R. Letellier, January 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
  - RecorDIM – Vienna, Austria; meeting report by Robin Letellier, September 15, 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 4)
  - RecorDIM – Vienna, Austria; meeting report by Robin Letellier, September 19, 2003 (Box 2018.IA.27-01)
  - RecorDIM – Vienna, Austria; field trip report by François LeBlanc, 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - RecorDIM activities report by Robin Letellier, 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - RecorDIM – Antalya, Turkey; field trip report by François LeBlanc, 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - RecorDIM – Article by François LeBlanc, 2003 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - RecorDIM – Leuven, Belgium; meeting report by Robin Letellier, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - RecorDIM – Leuven, Belgium; field trip report by François LeBlanc, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - RecorDIM – Istanbul, Turkey; Roundtable 4, meeting report by R. Letellier, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - ARIS, Rome, Italy - trip report by François LeBlanc, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - Guiding Principles Editorial Board – London, UK; field trip report by F. LeBlanc, 2004 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - RecorDIM – Paris, France; report by Robin Letellier, 2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - RecorDIM – Torino, Italy; field trip report by F. LeBlanc, 2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - ARIS-05 – Rome, Italy; field trip report by François LeBlanc, 2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - GCI Newsletter on recording and documentation, 2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - RecorDIM – Xi'an, China; field trip report by François LeBlanc, 2005 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - ARIS-07 – Rome, Italy; field trip report by François LeBlanc, 2006 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - RecorDIM – Rome, Italy; field trip report by François LeBlanc, 2006 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
  - RecorDIM – Ottawa, Canada; field trip report by François LeBlanc, 2007 (Box 2007.IA.38 - 5)
- Visuals
  - Guiding Principles Images, all images copyright J. Paul Getty Trust, 2007
  - RecorDIM_01 Guiding Principles Illustrations part 1 .jpg, .tif, .ai, 2003-2007
  - RecorDIM_02 Guiding Principles Illustrations part 2 .eps, .jpg, .pdf, .tif, 2005
  - RecorDIM_03 Meetings images .jpg, 2001-2004
  - RecorDIM_04 Meetings images Paris .jpg, 2005
  - RecorDIM_05 Meetings images .jpg, 2005-2006